<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc3987 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5988 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>
  <!ENTITY astreams PUBLIC '' 'http://docs.opensocial.org/download/attachments/4358254/astreams.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private="Activity Streams Working Group"?>
<rfc>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ActivityStreams">Links for Activity Streams</title>

    <author fullname="James M Snell" initials="J.M." surname="Snell">
      <organization>IBM</organization>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This specification details an extension to the JSON Activity Streams
      to express the serialization of arbitrary links to external resources 
      based on the Link Relation model defined by RFC 5988.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Link Properties">
    
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119" />.</t>
    
      <t>Section 3 of <xref target="RFC5988"/> defines a fundamental model
      for Links associated with Web accessible resources. This specification 
      applies that model as an optional extension to the JSON Activity Streams
      formats.</t>
      
      <t>Any object included within an Activity Stream structure MAY contain
      one or more extension properties whose names follow the "${rel}" naming
      pattern where {rel} is any registered or extension link relation type
      as defined by Section 4 of <xref target="RFC5988"/>; and whose value
      is either a JSON String containing an absolute <xref target="RFC3987">IRI</xref>
      that is the target of the link, or an array of JSON Strings containing 
      absolute IRIs in the case where multiple links with the same Link Relation
      must be specified.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>For example:</preamble><artwork>
  {
    "totalItems": 10,
    "$self" : "http://www.example.org/stream/page/1",
    "$next" : "http://www.example.org/stream/page/2",
    "$last" : "http://www.example.org/stream/page/10",
    "items" : [
      {
        "objectType" : "activity",
        "verb" : "post",
        "actor" : {
          "objectType" : "person",
          "displayName" : "joe",
          "id" : "acct:joe@example.org",
          "$self": "http://www.example.org/profiles/json/joe",
          "url": "http://www.example.org/profiles/html/joe"
        },
        "object" : {
          "objectType" : "note",
          "content" : "this note has links too",
          "$self" : "http://www.example.org/notes/json/1",
          "$http://example.com/ext/rel" : "http://.../foo",
          "url" : "http://www.example.org/notes/html/1"
        }
      }
    ]
  }
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>Implementations SHOULD interpret any field that begins with the
      US-ASCII dollar sign ($) character a Link Property unless the value is 
      anything other than a single absolute IRI or an array of absolute IRIs.</t>
      
      <t>When the value is specified as an array of absolute IRIs, the ordering
      of values within the array is considered insignificant. Each contained
      value is to be treated as a separate link. Values within the array SHOULD
      NOT be duplicated.</t>
      
      <t>When using extension link relation types, the {rel} portion of the 
      property name MAY be specified as an <xref target="RFC3987"/> IRI
      but MUST be converted to <xref target="RFC3986">URIs</xref> when compared 
      as required by Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC5988"/>.</t>
      
      <t>As defined in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC5988"/>, such properties
      can be viewed as statements of the form "The containing object has a 
      {relation type} resource at {target IRI}" where the {relation type} is
      identified by the property name minus the leading dollar sign character, 
      and the {target IRI} is provided by the property value.</t>
    
    </section>
   
   
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The mechanisms defined herein are subject to the same security considerations
      as all activities. The presence of Link properties within an object does
      not, by itself, introduce new security considerations to the basic processing
      of Activity Streams documents. However, when processing specific links of 
      a given Link Relation Type, additional security considerations specific to
      links of that type may apply. Implementors need to refer to the specifications
      of each Link Relation Type to determine the relevant considerations.</t>     
    </section>

    <section title="License">
    
      <t>This Specification is made available under the Open Web 
      Foundation Agreement Version 1.0, which is available at 
      http://www.openwebfoundation.org/legal/.</t>

      <t>You can review the signed copies of the Open Web Foundation 
      Agreement Version 1.0 for this Specification at 
      http://activitystrea.ms/licensing/, which may also include additional 
      parties to the authors.</t>

      <t>Your use of this Specification may be subject to other third party 
      rights. THIS SPECIFICATION IS PROVIDED "AS IS." The contributors 
      expressly disclaim any warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), 
      including implied warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, 
      fitness for a particular purpose, or title, related to the Specification. 
      The entire risk as to implementing or otherwise using the Specification 
      is assumed by the Specification implementer and user. IN NO EVENT WILL 
      ANY PARTY BE LIABLE TO ANY OTHER PARTY FOR LOST PROFITS OR ANY FORM OF 
      INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER 
      FROM ANY CAUSES OF ACTION OF ANY KIND WITH RESPECT TO THIS SPECIFICATION 
      OR ITS GOVERNING AGREEMENT, WHETHER BASED ON BREACH OF CONTRACT, TORT 
      (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE), OR OTHERWISE, AND WHETHER OR NOT THE OTHER PARTY 
      HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</t>
    
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3987;
      &rfc3986;
      &rfc5988;  
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>